<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Twilio | ]]></title>
  <link href="http://cheshireoctopus.github.io/blog/categories/twilio/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cheshireoctopus.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-22T23:58:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://cheshireoctopus.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chandler Moisen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twilio on Rails: SMS Basics]]></title>
    <link href="http://cheshireoctopus.github.io/blog/2013/10/22/twilio-on-rails-sms-basics/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-22T19:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cheshireoctopus.github.io/blog/2013/10/22/twilio-on-rails-sms-basics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/Twilio/Logo.png" title="&lsquo;Twilio Logo&rsquo; &lsquo;Twilio Logo&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><a href="www.twilio.com">Twilio</a> is an awesome platform that makes it super easy to add SMS, voice, and VOIP functionality to your web applications.</p>

<p>This tutorial will show you how to set up an extremely simple Ruby on Rails application that uses Twilio to send SMS messages from your
browser. It&rsquo;s probably best that you have a basic understanding of RoR.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Quick Start</h2>

<h4>Twilio Setup</h4>

<p><strong>1:</strong> <a href="https://www.twilio.com/try-twilio">Sign up</a> for free using a telephone number that you have access to &ndash; preferably your cell &ndash; as you will
have to verify your account via SMS.</p>

<p><strong>2:</strong> Twilio will automatically generate a telephone number for you. In my experience, these generated numbers are issued with
the same area code as the original number you signed up with. <strong>Note:</strong> you can customize your number if you so wish.</p>

<p>After you&rsquo;ve made it through the login, you should be welcomed with this screen:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Twilio/Twilio1.png" title="&lsquo;Twilio Home&rsquo; &lsquo;Twilio Home&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Make a note of both the <strong>ACCOUNT SID</strong> and the <strong>AUTH TOKEN</strong> &ndash; you will need both of these later. To see the latter, click on the lock to view it.</p>

<p><strong>3:</strong> I like to save my Twilio numbers in my cell because I have a terrible memory. As you can guess, I often forget to do even that. Visiting the &lsquo;Numbers&rsquo;
pane on the Twilio dashboard &ndash; pictured below &ndash; provide them for you.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Twilio/Number.png" title="&lsquo;Twilio Number&rsquo; &lsquo;Twilio Number&rsquo;" ></p>

<h4>Rails Setup</h4>

<p><strong>1:</strong> First, create the Rails application, in this case thought-provokingly named &lsquo;twilio_app&rsquo;. We don&rsquo;t need the index.html that Rails so graciously provides &ndash;
 toss it, you don&rsquo;t need that noise.</p>

<pre><code>rails g new twilio_app
rm public/index.html
</code></pre>

<p><strong>2:</strong> Twilio compiled a gem which makes Rails integration realtively painless. Check out the <a href="http://twilio-ruby.readthedocs.org/en/latest/">documentation</a>
and add it in the Gemfile. Make sure to bundle!</p>

<pre><code>#Gemfile

gem 'twilio-ruby'
</code></pre>

<p><strong>3:</strong> Next, we will generate a controller which will be responsbile for making sense of our app&rsquo;s request and produce the appropriate output. <strong>Note:</strong> this
method of controller generation creates a bunch of extra files you do not need for this application.</p>

<pre><code>rails g controller twilio
</code></pre>

<p><strong>4</strong>: In the controller you just created, add a method &lsquo;send_sms&rsquo; which will send the SMS&rsquo;s. We will come back to this in a moment.</p>

<pre><code>class TwilioController &lt; ApplicationController

  def send_sms
  end

end
</code></pre>

<p><strong>5:</strong> We&rsquo;re making headway on the back-end, but we need do some barebones front-end functionality. Create a file <strong>&lsquo;index.html.erb&rsquo;</strong> that your Twilio
controller has access to. Make sure this file is located in the following directory: <strong>twilio_app/app/views/layouts</strong>. In this file we are going to create a simple form which will allow the user to input a phone number and a message. Make sure the form&rsquo;s action directs to <strong>&lsquo;/send_sms&rsquo;</strong> and the method is
 <strong>&lsquo;POST&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<pre><code>#index.html.erb

&lt;h1&gt;TWILIO!!!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;%= form_tag('/send_sms', method: 'POST') do %&gt;
&lt;input type="text" placeholder="enter number" name="number"&gt;
&lt;input type="text" placeholder="enter message here" name="message"&gt;
&lt;button type="submit"&gt;Submit&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;% end %&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Your <strong>index.html.erb</strong> should look like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Twilio/Index.png" title="&lsquo;Index.html page&rsquo; &lsquo;Index.html page&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><strong>6:</strong> Now, we&rsquo;ve made our view and controller, let&rsquo;s connect them via routes.rb. Clear out the comments in the <strong>routes.rb</strong> file, build a root path that directs to <strong>index.html.erb</strong>, and then another path that will post the information from the form we just built to the <strong>send_sms</strong> method in the Twilio controller.</p>

<pre><code>TwilioApp::Application.routes.draw do

  root :to =&gt; 'twilio#index'
  post '/send_sms' =&gt; 'twilio#send_sms'

end
</code></pre>

<p><strong>7:</strong> Alright, last step. Do you still remember your <strong>ACCOUNT SID</strong>, <strong>AUTH TOKEN</strong>, and <strong>Twilio phone number</strong>? We&rsquo;re going to add these to our Twilio controller&rsquo;s <strong>send_sms</strong> method to enable our application to send texts.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll show you my code, then walk you through it line by line.</p>

<pre><code>1 class TwilioController &lt; ApplicationController
2
3  def send_sms
4   message = params[:message]
5   number = params[:number]
6   account_sid = 'XXXyour account sid should be hereXXX'
7   auth_token = 'XXXyour auth token should be hereXXX'
8
9   @client = Twilio::REST::Client.new account_sid, auth_token
10
11  @message = @client.account.messages.create({:to =&gt; "+1"+"#{number}",
12                                  :from =&gt; "+12813308004",
13                                   :body =&gt; "#{message}"})
14   redirect_to '/'
15  end
16
17 end
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li><strong>1:</strong> Opens the TwilioController</li>
<li><strong>3:</strong> Defines the <strong>&lsquo;send_sms&rsquo;</strong> method</li>
<li><strong>4:</strong> Takes the <strong>message</strong> input from the form in <strong>index.html.erb</strong> as a paramater and assigns it to the variable &lsquo;message&rsquo;</li>
<li><strong>5:</strong> Takes the <strong>number</strong> input from the form in <strong>index.html.erb</strong> as a paramater and assigns it to the variable &lsquo;number&rsquo;</li>
<li><strong>6:</strong> Stores your <strong>ACCOUNT SID</strong> as a variable</li>
<li><strong>7:</strong> Stores your <strong>AUTH TOKEN</strong> as a variable</li>
<li><strong>9:</strong> Instatiates a Twilio Rest Client as <strong>@client</strong>, which stores the authentication parameters on lines 6 and 7 (account_sid and auth_token, respectively), and enables the <strong>send_sms</strong> method to make HTTP request to Twilio. <a href="http://rubydoc.info/github/twilio/twilio-ruby/Twilio/REST/Client">More info&hellip;</a></li>
<li><strong>11-13:</strong> Creates a message, stored as the variable <strong>@message</strong>, which takes a hash as an argument. The hash should include: <strong>:to</strong>, <strong>:from</strong>, and <strong>:body</strong>. <strong>:to</strong> interpolates the variable <strong>number</strong>, and represents the recipeint of the SMS. <strong>:from</strong> should be your Twilio number stored in the following format: +12813308004. <strong>:body</strong> interpolates the <strong>message</strong> variable which contains the message entered on <strong>index.html.erb</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>14</strong> After the SMS is processed and sent, this redirects the user back to the root directory, or, in our case, <strong>index.html.erb</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Outcome</h2>

<p>Assuming the code is correct, run the application locally and send yourself a message.</p>

<p>If everything works out, you should be able to send SMS messages from your browser!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Twilio/Cat.png" title="&lsquo;Cat&rsquo; &lsquo;Cat&rsquo;" ></p>

<h2>Caveats</h2>

<p>As this application was developed using Twilio&rsquo;s free service, you can only send texts to the phone number that you verified your Twilio account with. To mess with your friends, activate your Twilio account by adding a credit card. Individual texts cost less that $.01&hellip;</p>

<h2>Next Steps</h2>

<p>One day I will write a follow up, but for now, check out this <a href="https://github.com/crabasa/twilio-rails-demo">github repo</a> for an idea of where else you can take Twilio and Rails.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
